John Skutel Collection
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
John Skutel Collection
1831-1957
1850s-1900s
Skutel, John
BHC-MSS 0009
3 linear feet 1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Collected by John Skutel, a private collector who placed his materials up for auction in 1989. The collection contains material related to P.T. Barnum and associates, which is heavily represented by the Bridgeport History Center's P.T. Barnum Research Collection (BHC-MSS 00001). Of note in the Skutel Collection is the original contract that signed M. Lavinia Warren to P.T. Barnum's management, and the original typescript of Warren's autobiography.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Biography
John Skutel was a private collector of material related to P.T. Barnum.
Scope and Content of Collection
John Skutel collected material related to P.T. Barnum and his performers. While there are some items of Jenny Lind and Charles S. Stratton, also known as General Tom Thumb, in the materials, M. Lavinia Warren is the most heavily represented. There is no overarching scope beyond all of the connections to Barnum. Included in the collection are a number of mass market books, including multiple copies of Struggles and Triumphs, P.T. Barnum's autobiography.
Arrangement
Arranged by subject, then chronologically.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Barnum, P.T. (Phineas Taylor), 1810-1891; Bailey, James Anthony, 1847-1906; Lind, Jenny, 1820-1887; Magri, M. Lavinia (Mercy Lavinia), 1841-1919; Thumb, Tom, 1838-1883; Barnum & London Circus; Barnum and Bailey; Barnum's American Museum
- Inventory
  - Letterhead, PT Barnum’s marvelous drawing room aggregation, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Program, Banquet to welcome Mr. PT Barnum to England, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Map, Denver showing Barnum’s property c., 1880-1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Program, Barnum’s Wonders, Hindoo Hairy Family, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript, Philo Barnum, Sheriff and US Deputy Marshall (2 pieces), 1905 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Booklet, “Legends of the blue hills” with strange Barnum reference on p. 10, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Article, PT Barnum, Showman and humorist, by Joel Benton from Century Magazine, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter, John Niles to Zalman Wildman, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter, Gideon Welles to Zalman Wildman, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, I.W. Barnum c., 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript, PT Barnum biography with photos by George Gordy cover, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript, PT Barnum biography with photos by George Gordy, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Handbill, Masonic festival with GL Stratton on the program, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book, General Tom Thumb’s 3 Years Tour around the World by Sylvester Bleeker and The Tale of Tom Thumb, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Contract signing M. Lavinia Warren to P.T. Barnum’s employ, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter, Countess Magri to Mrs. Conroy, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Original typescript for Autobiography of Mrs. Tom Thumb by M. Lavinia Warren, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Typescript for “My last chapter” by M. Lavinia Warren, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Postcards and tickets, 2 postcards from Mrs. Tom Thumb at Midget City c. 1910s, 2 tickets to General Tom Thumb’s Entertainment, undated; colored engraving of Mr. and Mrs. Tom Thumb. C., 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - “The story that never grows old”, by Benjamin Bump, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sheet music, the Tom Thumb Polka, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Small items, Invitation to Mrs. Tom Thumb’s 74th birthday; small 1-page print of the history of Mr. and Mrs. Tom Thumb; a Tom Thumb children’s book, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Jenny Lind Album (autograph book), 1905 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Program, the Barnum Festival, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sheet music, Tom Thumb Polka, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jenny Lind songbook, c., 1850-1859 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper, Utica Morning Herald and Daily Gazette; Tom Thumb’s Wedding on front page, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper, Harper’s Weekly Journal of Civilization featuring the Fairy Wedding, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - P.T. Barnum's Advanced Courier, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - American Agriculturalist, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - PT Barnum’s menagerie, text and illustrations arranged for little people by PT Barnum and Sarah J. Burke, 1890-1899 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Missing: General Tom Thumb and his lady by Romaine, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)